Guide to the Alexandre Polovtsoff Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Alexandre Polovtsoff papers
1918-1934
MS 403
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
1.5
(6 boxes)
Notes, manuscripts, and transcript copies of Alexandre Polovtsoff's (1867-1934) writings after his emigration from Russia in 1918. Included are autobiographical materials, articles on Russian art, the imperial palaces, and Russian historical figures; also, translations of the Journal de Voyage en Russie by Francisco de Miranda, and The Curse of Wit by A. S. Griboedov.
Polovtsoff, Alexandre, 1867-
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Deposited by Madame Sophie Polovtsoff, 1964.
Biographical / Historical
Born in St. Petersburg in 1867, Polovtsoff grew up amid the cultivated society of the era; as a young man, he served several years in the cavalry (1888-1892), afterwards entering the Ministry of Internal Affairs, where he held responsible positions and travelled extensively through Russia and the outlying provinces. He also served as a foreign diplomat, one of his more protracted assignments being a post with the Russian Embassy in Bombay, 1906-1909. He maintained an active interest in Russian art and engaged in such activities as the organization of the Exhibition of Russian Art in London in 1935, also writing several articles and speeches on the subject.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists primarily of notes, manuscripts and typescript copies of the writings of Alexandre Polovtsoff, between the time of his emigration from Russia in 1918 and his death. His autobiographical works contain reminiscences from his youth and accounts of his later official work. His book, Les trésors d'art en Russie sous le régime bolchéviste, published in Paris, 1919, and found here in manuscript form as "Le Bolchévisme et les palais imperiaux," describes his efforts to protect the imperial palaces of Russia immediately after the Revolution in 1917, before his emigration.
The bulk of the collection consists of various historical writings. The only one of these works to have been published is Les Favoris de Catherine la Grande, Paris, 1939; but the collection contains an extended study of Peter the Great, and articles, sketches, and notes on various Russian monarchs and other historical figures. There are also some translations: the Journal de Voyage en Russie of Don Francisco de Miranda (from Spanish), and The Curse of Wit of A. S. Griboedov (from Russian).
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Europe; Soviet Union -- History; Historians; Catherine, Empress of Russia, II, 1729-1796; Griboyedov, Aleksandr Sergeyevich, 1795-1829; Miranda, Francisco de, 1750-1816; Peter, Emperor of Russia, I, 1672-1725; Polovtsoff, Alexandre, 1867-
- Inventory of the Papers
  - Historical writings: Peter I, emperor of Russia, 1672-1725; Catherine I, empress of Russia, d. 1727; Elizabeth, empress of Russia, 1709-1762
    - Notes on Peter I (notebook) (Box 1, Folder 1a)
    - "Pierre le Grand vu par un temoin étranger" [Bergholz] (notebook) (Box 1, Folder 1b)
    - Petr Veliki? [Peter the Great] p.257-272, "L'oeuvre de Pierre le Grand..." [On Elizabeth, empress of Russia] (notebook) (Box 1, Folder 1c)
    - Petr Velikiĭ [Peter the Great] Vol. I (typescript) (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Petr Velikiĭ [Peter the Great] Vol. II (typescript) (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - "Catherine I of Russia" (typescript) (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - "The daughter of Peter the Great (Elizabeth, Empress of Russia)" (notebook) (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Historical writings: Catherine II, empress of Russia, 1729-1796; Paul I, emperor of Russia, 1754-1801; Marie Feodorovna, empress consort of Paul I, 1759-1828
    - Notes on Les Favoris de la Grande Catherine (notebook) (Box 2, Folder 1a)
    - Notes on Les Favoris de Catherine II (13 p., typescript) (Box 2, Folder 1b)
    - "Lettres de Catherine II a Mlle. Liovchine," 22 Aug 1771 - 1775 (notebook, copy by Polovtsoff) (Box 2, Folder 1c)
    - "Lettres de Mlle. Liovchine a Catherine II," winter 1771 - 9 Apr 1780 (copy by Polovtsoff) (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - "Yubileĭ Smol'nogo" [On Smolny, convent school founded by Catherine II] (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - "Catherine II et Mlle. Liovchine" (notebook) (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - "Ob odnoĭ knige" [Review of Les Favoris de Catherine II ] (typescript, carbon copy) (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - "Catherine II" (typescript) (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Les Favoris de Catherine II (typescript) (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - "Le Voyage du Comte et de la Comtesse du Nord" [Paul I and Marie Feodorovna] (notebook) (Box 2, Folder 3a)
    - "Yubile? Smol'nogo" (notebook) (Box 2, Folder 3b)
      General
      See: box 2, folder 1
    - "The Count and Countess of the North" [Paul I and Marie Feodorovna] (Box 2, Folder 3c)
    - "To many people the Exhibition of Russian Art at Belgrave Square...." (notebook) (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - "Un Portrait inédit de la Comtesse du Nord" [Marie Feodorovna] (typescript) (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Historical writings: Various figures in Russian history
    - "Pushkin – peve Rossii" [On A. S. Pushkin (1799-1837)] (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - "Les Chinois quoique beaucoup plus libre à une époque reculée que nous..." [essay on early conditions in Russia] (notebook) (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Copy of letter of Count Alexander Andreevich Bezborodko to "Mesdemoiselles les grises, de la Communauté de Demoiselles Nobles" St. Petersburg, 3 May 1770 (manuscript) (Box 3, Folder 1)
      Bezborodko (1746-1799) was head of dept. of foreign affairs and advisor to Catherine II and Paul I.
    - "Extraits des Memoires de Photius," copied from "Archives Russes," 1869, page 937 (Box 3, Folder 1)
      Archimandrite Photius (Peter Nikitich Spasky, 1792-1838) was a reactionary ecclesiastical leader during the reign of Alexander I.
    - Essay (in Russian) on Count Ilarion Ivanovich Vorontsov-Dashkov (Box 3, Folder 1)
      Vorontsov-Dashkov (1837-1916) was minister of the imperial household and later viceroy of the Caucasus.
      See also: box 4, folder 2
    - Extraits des memoires d'A. Gribovsky (écrits en 1830) [On the court of Catherine II] (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Notes on Catherine II (notebook) (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - "Romanoff (Dynasty)" (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - "Un Grand Seigneur Russe Jacobin" [Stroganoff, Alexander, count, 1733-1795] (typescript) (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - "Polovt︠s︡y" by Alexander Saltykov (newspaper clipping, probably printed in Paris, 1935) (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - "Un espagnol à la cour de Catherine II" [Don Francisco de Miranda] (typescript, carbon copy) (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Journal de Voyage en Russie by Don Francisco de Miranda [trans. by A. A. Polovtsoff and Léon Bobrinsky] (typescript) (Box 3, Folder 2)
      - Vol. 1 (Box 3, Folder 3)
      - Vol. 2 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Writings on the imperial palaces and Russian art
    General note
    See also: box 2, folder 3 box 5, folder 1
    - "St. Petersbourg, cité impériale" (notebook) (Box 4, Folder 1a)
    - "Krasota S. Peterburga" (notebook) (Box 4, Folder 1b)
    - "Russian Art, a historical survey" (Box 4, Folder 2a)
    - "Graf I. I. Voront?s?ov" [Count I. I. Vorontsov, (1837-1916)] (notebook) (Box 4, Folder 2b)
    - "Some Notes on the St. Petersburg Tapestry Works" (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - "A Propos du palais de Pavlovsk" (notebook) (Box 4, Folder 3a)
    - "Versailles et les Résidences Impériales de Russie" (printed illustrations, 2 p., 1922) (Box 4, Folder 3b)
    - "Palais Russes du XVIII s." (typescript, carbon copy) (Box 4, Folder 3c)
    - "Versailles et les Résidences Impériales de Russie" (manuscript) (Box 4, Folder 3d)
    - "Je vais vous parler des palais impériales de Russie..." (typescript, carbon copy) (Box 4, Folder 3e)
    - "Exhibition of Russian Art" (printed catalogue, London, 1935) (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - "Une exposition retrospective d'art russe vient de s'ouvrir à Londres..." (Box 4, Folder 4)
      See also: box 2, folder 3
      See also: box 5, folder 1
  - Autobiographical material
    - "Imperial Palaces under Bolshevism" (notebook) (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Autobiographical Notes ("Je commence à écrire ces notes...") (notebook) (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Bolshévisme et les palais impériaux (notebook) (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - "They have no virtue" [on the Bolshevik Revolution, and its effect on industry] (manuscript) (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - "Vospominanie" [Memoirs] (typescript, carbon copy) (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Miscellaneous
    1024-after 1075, m. Henry I of France
    empress consort of Napoleon III, 1826-1920
    Giovanna I, queen of Naples, d.1382; Giovanna II, queen of Naples
    Chudleigh, Elizabeth, countess of Bristol, calling herself Duchess of Kingston, 1720-1788
    - "Anna Yaroslavna Queen of France" (notebook) (Box 6, Folder 1a)
    - Notes sur 1'Impératrice Eugénie (manuscript) (Box 6, Folder 1b)
    - "Two Angevin Queens" (typescript, carbon copy) (Box 6, Folder 1c)
    - "The Duchess of Kingston" [apparently notes for a movie scenario] (notebook) (Box 6, Folder 1d)
    - "Internationale avant la lettre" (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - "The Spell of the Throne in Russia" (notebook) (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - "Le Comte Alexander Matveievitch Dimitriev-Mamonov, 1758-1803" (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Une Internationale avant la lettre (texte écourté) (notebook) (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - "Rasprodazha [?] Ėrmitazha" (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Le Musée d'Ajaccio (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - The Curse of Wit by A. S. Griboyedov, 1795-1829 [trans. A. A. Polovtsoff] (Box 6, Folder 2)
      - Acts I-III (notebook) (Box 6, Folder 3)
      - Act IV (notebook) (Box 6, Folder 3)
      - Typescript (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Miscellaneous notes & notebooks
      - Manuscript, 6 pieces (Box 6, Folder 4)
      - Manuscript, 10 pages (Box 6, Folder 4)
      - Manuscript, 9 pages (Box 6, Folder 4)
      - Manuscript, 15 pages (Box 6, Folder 4)
      - Notebooks ["No. 2 and No. 3"] (Box 6, Folder 4)